I'm going to be presenting on
a poetry portfolio
I created called connected disconnected.
This originated from some coursework
I was doing
at the University of Central Florida,
and the text and technology program
that I ultimately turned into a larger
AI assistant work.
This was the theme of
my poetry, was inspired by the connection
between technology and society,
which kind of mirrored my writing process
of working alongside
cloud code while keeping my own authorship
of my poetry and works.
And this was inspired by my interest
in seeing
if AI was able to evoke emotion
through my own prompting.
So, of course, as we know, like
AI is not capable
of emotional intelligence,
but through specific prompting,
terms and guidance,
I wanted to see if I could use cloud code
to create emotional graphics that mirrored
the actions of my own written poetry.
So this was inspired by looking at how,
you know, in the humanities,
our understanding of character, style,
image and creativity
and how sometimes that can get buried
within the use of AI
and the overshadowing of the technical
aspects of AI.
So I wanted to look at how it can be used
for creativity
through like rhetorical prompting
with my background in rhetoric.
So I wanted to start with my own poetry,
which connects humans through
lived experiences, subjects and surveys,
and then use AI to handle
the technical tasks.
In order to remediate my site
and create this hypertext
and digital portfolio
where my poems can reside.
And this was heavily
based on my studies on Hayles
and looking at how to create a partnership
between humans and technology
so that humans don't get lost
in their roles of implementing technology
and creative spaces.
So I'm going to be speaking a bit
about why I chose to use
AI with my poetry,
how I chose the platform that I used,
some of the inspiration
behind that in terms of scholarship,
and then some examples from my site.
So you can see kind of what I was building
and the goals of my live demo,
which I will share a QR code
to at the end.
So looking at agent versus
generative AI, obviously there's a place
for generative AI.
It can be a good brainstorming tool
that can help with a lot of like workflows
and things like that.
But the purpose of this project,
I really wanted to ensure that my voice
landed in the final portfolio.
So I turned to a genetic
AI to ensure that the technical support
I was doing was strictly for
for graphics and automation tools
and coding and things like that.
So when I learned about cloud code,
I had experimented with that a bit
on the first poem
and was really pleased with
some of the results was able to get,
which in turn led me to create
the final portfolio and the larger project
that I'll be showing today.
So in terms of the theoretical framework,
as I mentioned,
this borrowed heavily from Hayles,
but I ultimately decided to step further
and bring in my rhetoric background
into this prompting.
So I wanted to take this
all the way back to Aristotle
and think about this in terms of pathos,
because I wanted to see
if I connected that term to this,
if it could understand how to apply
emotional graphics to my work,
and how rhetoric could speak to
AI through creative writing.
So I also turned to the concept
of the medium
as the message
for a lot of these graphics.
Because when I was doing the prompting
with Claude Code, I was very specific
in inputting that I didn't want these
to just be like artistic features
that represented the poems,
but I wanted them to be something
that the audience participates in,
and that when they click around
and they're seeing these graphics, it's
part of the poem and the final results, so
that my audience is actually contributing
to the meaning and themes of my poem.
So here's an example of the first poem
that's on my site.
So in here I actually,
through my prompting, the Cloud Code
wanted the poems
to be in the interface of a phone.
So again, with the themes of my poem,
we have society and technology.
So this entire portfolio sort of resembles
a push and pull of that.
So what we gain and lose,
we have the accessibility of a phone,
easy access to communication,
but then we have the aspect
of what gets taken away
in relationships or physical settings
and things like that.
So when a user clicks into the icon,
they can choose any one of those icons
on the left that they want,
and it will open up an icon
that each has a poem
that resides within it.
So for example,
the messaging app, if they go in there,
they're going to actually respond
to the poem in a text thread.
If they respond negatively to technology,
they're going to get this outcome on
figure four
that says message cannot be delivered.
So again,
this graphic isn't just about an esthetic,
but it actually changes
the final result of the poem
based on how the audience feels.
And then the maps on sort of resembles
navigating
one's own opinions
or beliefs in the poem.
So all of these esthetic choices
were used to help
design the theme
and outcome of my opponent cells.
So here we
have the next poem,
which was more of a word cluster.
So this one had a range of words
that a user can go and click on.
When they click on a word,
it opens up its own poem.
So a poem resides
within each of these words.
And when I was
prompting for this particular poem,
I was really looking at juxtaposition.
So I wanted words
that said like human touch, love,
in contrast with things
like ghost and memory and data.
And when a user clicks and pauses
on a word, it creates a heart shape on.
This creates imagery
that represents, again,
that human connection,
which juxtaposes with the
sort of mechanical
words and poems that are placed here.
So lastly, we have when
pixels cry again using juxtaposition
to think of something like pixels.
Using a bit of humor here as well,
having a little song with this one.
And then we have like the tears
in the background to kind of create this
like melodramatic effect.
So when users hover over
certain words in here,
you're going to get a glitch
effect, you're going to have connection
failed and tears in the background.
So I'm kind of playing around
with the aspect of AI
not really being able to be emotional
as sort of
like the humor
and the actions behind the words.
So the prompting process and my methods
utilize rhetorical analysis,
AI literacy and decoding poetic devices.
So ultimately I was driven
by asking it to create pesos through
specific images, such as like the rain
or In the tears and things like that.
And I was using
AI literacy
literacy to create iterations of this.
So whenever it would do something that
didn't produce the result that I wanted,
I would have to be a lot more specific
with my language, tie more terms to it,
and just to kind of get that final result
that I was looking for.
And ultimately, I found that feeding
at specific poetic devices
was really helpful in that
because it was able to use
these poetic devices to create
a little bit more of an emotional appeal.
For example, if I said like juxtaposition,
the word cluster was able to create that
heart with that poem
that was a bit more mechanical
and that kind of produced
a more like dramatic effect.
So I found that to be the most useful
in kind of
pushing the boundaries of emotion
with cloud code,
given the limitations that, of course,
are going to fall into place of that.
So of course, with this, there's
going to be limitations.
I came in with some pretty extravagant
ideas on some things that I wanted to do
in terms of like, artistic,
you know, like faces and things like that.
I really I wanted there for the pixel one,
I wanted like more
of a realistic face and somebody's crying,
you know, a I just can't produce that.
So I had to turn to
smaller symbols
that just resembled my own writing,
just kind of keeping that at the forefront
and using this as something
that just brought my poetry
into digital spaces, and looking more
at giving agency to the users,
and that hypertext features versus
something that might be more artistic
and elaborate overall,
is pretty pleased with the final results.
Given the limitations of AI,
and just especially in the sense
of the audience being able to contribute
to the final meaning of the poem
in some way, which spoke to kind of
the emotional aspect that I was going for.
So all in all,
given the limitations of AI,
I was pleased with cloud code
and its ability to create graphics
that resemble my writing
and still keeping my authorship there.
So ultimately, going back to
my original question
of why I chose to work with
AI as a rhetoric student,
I have grappled with some of these
like technical platforms and softwares,
but ultimately with my focus on writing
cloud code allowed me
to create all of these visions that I had,
bring my poetry into new spaces without
having to be fluent in all of these
languages and platforms and technologies.
So this screenshot on the left
just kind of shows,
like all of those things
that I would have to be fluent in
to done this manually
without the assistance of cloud code.
So that was kind of part
of the inspiration behind this project
as well,
was the ability to focus on my writing
while still grappling with
some of these remediation and exploring
digital poetry and ways that that fit
with my skill sets and my ultimate goals.
So if anybody
wants to see this live,
it does work on a mobile device.
Of course, it's
a little easier on a desktop,
but you definitely can scan it
and check it out
if you have any questions about it.
I'm happy to answer that for anybody
that wants to explore it further.
Again, each one in the portfolio
is a different genre of poetry,
so you can click on them
and kind of explore what John is
you want to experiment with.
And there's some poems and here
that I didn't touch on in the figures
or screenshots.
So you'll see new materials.
So if you have questions
about that as well and how to answer them.
But ultimately I felt that AI was useful
in handling
the technical tools, as I mentioned,
and that my place as a writer
student was really useful in prompting,
which of course
influenced the final result
and what I achieved, and kind of showing
how writing does
have a place in the collaboration with AI.
And in the future,
I definitely want to broaden this work,
and I would like to do something user
testing on this as well,
just to see how audiences interpret it
from their viewpoint,
and see how I can make
additional iterations based on that.
So thank you very much.